I'd like to introduce
our speaker for today.
So Shrimai is an AI
Scientist at Mistral AI,
as well as an Adjunct
Professor at Boston University.
And her research focuses on
advancing large language models
or LLMs, particularly improving
their reasoning capabilities.
So prior to this, she
was lead contributor
to NVIDIA's Nemo Tron
family of models,
working on data curation,
pre-training, and scaling.
Her work emphasizes optimizing
pre-training pipelines,
including data
selection, blending,
and ordering strategies to
maximize downstream model
performance.
So without further ado,
I'll hand it off to Shrimai.
[APPLAUSE]
Hello, everyone.
Yeah, thank you for
that introduction.
Yeah, I joined
Mistral this Monday.
But today, I'll be talking
about a lot of my work I've
done during my time at NVIDIA.
And if any of you are
interested to know
about Mistral AI or
opportunities at Mistral AI,
please feel free to email
me at my email address.
And I'm also here after the
class to answer any questions.
So let's get started.
So today, I'll be talking about
from next-token prediction
to next-generation
of intelligence.
And what's the future of
pre-training in general?
Before I get started,
this according to me,
is the recipe to
build a SOTA LLM.
And it has four key components.
You need smart data.
You need a lot of high-quality
data which is diverse.
You need to be able to do good
filtering, de-duplication,
and so on.
You need smart architecture.
So as you know,
architectures are evolving.
From transformers, we now have
Mamba2 hybrid architectures
and so on.
You need smart algorithms.
How can you build
advanced training recipes?
And you, obviously,
need smart collaboration
between pre-training,
post-training teams,
research, and
engineering and so on.
So, what is the work that
we have done in building
smart data for LLMs?
I just want to give a
brief overview of that.
So during my time
at NVIDIA, I was
able to contribute towards MIND,
which is a synthetic dialogues.
But they are all
related to math.
Nemotron-CC-Math,
which is common math
that is passed from
Common Crawl documents.
And all of this data, including
the Nemotron Nano 2 dataset,
it's available in an open-source
manner on Hugging Face.
We also developed
prismatic synthesis,
which encourages diversity
in synthetic data generation.
And Nemotron-CrossThink,
which was a dataset more
geared towards reasoning
beyond math and code.
And this particular
Nemotron-CrossThink dataset
became one of the
most trending datasets
from NVIDIA on Hugging Face
the week that it was released.
But today, I'll be talking
about building smart algorithms
for LLMs.
And in particular, I want to
talk about three of our works--
maximizing your data's
potential, front-loading
reasoning, and RLP, which
is using reinforcement
as a pre-training objective.
So before I get started,
I want to give you
an overview of what I'm
going to be talking about,
and what are the key
components of what
I'm going to be talking about?
So let's say there
are these four kids--
Pascal, Volta,
Ampere, and Hopper.
They all have access
to the exact same data,
the exact amount of
data, quality of data.
Everything is same.
But what is different
for these four kids
is how they learn
from this data.
And there are three
key components there.
One is curriculum which is the
order in which you see the data.
Second is front-loading
reasoning.
What I mean by that
is all four of them
have access to high-quality
reasoning data.
But, how do they use it?
Do they use it early on?
Or do they wait later
on in life to use it?
And I like to give
an analogy over here
with the American education
system, where there
is this concept of
taking AP classes, which
is college level classes
during your schooling years.
And the idea behind that
is that you will do well
if you do-- if you take
those classes during school,
then you'll not only
do well in school,
but you'll also do
well in college.
So that basically
captures the idea
behind front-loading reasoning.
And then finally, learning
through thinking, not just
observing.
So these are the
three key strategies.
And let's see how
these four kids learn
using these three strategies.
So Pascal, unfortunately,
does not follow a curriculum.
The data that's
available to him,
he is just reading it randomly.
He may read one text from
history, one very advanced math
document, and then a
very basic math document.
He does not utilize the
reasoning high-quality data
that is available to him.
He just never reads it.
And finally, he does not
learn through thinking.
Volta, on the other hand,
follows a curriculum
that is, she reads the documents
in a certain order and finds out
that it's beneficial,
but she decides
not to read the high-quality
documents available to her,
and she also doesn't
learn through thinking.
Ampere follows a curriculum and
uses the reasoning documents
that are available
to him, but he also
doesn't learn through thinking.
And finally, Hopper learns
through a curriculum.
She also makes good use of
the high quality documents
that she has, and she also
learns through thinking
and engaging with the material.
She's not just
reading the material.
So this is what we will go
over throughout the whole talk.
I'm going to be showing
comparisons between Pascal,
Volta, Ampere, and Hopper.
So first, let's cover
maximize your data's potential
and enhancing LLM accuracy
with two-phase pre-training.
So as you all know,
LLMs today are
trained on trillions
and trillions of tokens.
And they come from vast
sources, like all kinds
of diverse sources that are
legal documents, books, papers,
web crawl, which is
everything and anything.
And you have math documents.
And this is an analysis
done by Epoch AI, where
it shows how much data is
consumed by the LLMs today.
And it projects that by
somewhere around 2030,
LLMs would consume more than
95% of human generated data.
And the blue curve here is what
I want you to follow and see
that in somewhere 2021,
when GPT-3 was trained,
it was trained on hundreds
of billions of tokens.
But Llama 3, which
was in late 2024,
was trained on tens of
trillions of tokens.
And that's where we are today.
And soon we will consume all
of the human-generated data.
So now that you have all these
different data sources, now
there are two important
questions to answer.
First is that, how do you weigh
these different data sources?
Which is that, how do
you decide which document
is a better quality document
and which document is not?
And, how do you order these
different data sources?
So again, like
curriculum, how do you
know which document
to read first
and which document to
read later on in life?
So to create an optimal
blend or data mixture,
we follow this simple pipeline
where you have all this data
and you do quality estimations.
So you build quality
classifiers and you
try to estimate what's the
quality of each of your data
source.
And the idea then, when you're
creating your optimal data
mixture, is that data sources
that have the same quality,
they should be weighed
similarly in your data mixture.
And higher quality
datasets must be
weighed higher than medium
and low quality data sources.
Next, you want to
do epoch estimation.
This is basically estimating how
many repeats of a data source
you want to see.
So to get the most juice out of
your high quality data source
especially, you
want to estimate,
what is the maximum
number of repeats
you want to see of this
particular data source
before it starts giving
diminishing gains
on your downstream tasks?
So you'll estimate the quality.
You'll estimate the
number of repeats.
And based on this, you create
your blend, optimal blend
or your optimal data mixture.
And then for
curriculum, we follow
a two-phase pre-training
approach, where in phase 1,
the idea is to encourage
diversity in data.
So you want to be able to
expose the model to as much data
as you can and as
diverse data as you can,
where this is also mostly
the data mixture looks
like it has a lot of web
crawl, including both medium
and low quality crawl.
You also show lower number of
epochs of high quality data
sources at this time.
And then in phase
2, the emphasis
is only on high quality
data, that is, only
on higher number of epochs
of high quality data
sources like math,
Wikipedia, code, and so on.
So this is the
two-phase approach.
And this is what we follow
in our pre-training.
And what are the baselines
for this approach?
So first is natural
distribution.
So you have three
axes-- quality, epochs,
and order of the data.
So in natural distribution,
it's basically
you don't care what is
the quality of the data
or, how many repeats should
I see of a particular data?
In natural distribution,
the way you
create the blend is that you
just draw samples from a data
source, and they are equivalent
to how many tokens are
available in that data source.
So if you have a data source,
which is low in quality,
but it is a huge
data source, it is
very large in number
of tokens, then
you will see more
of that data source
just because it has more
tokens available in it.
And in this baseline,
you also don't
show any ordering of the data.
The second is where you
create an optimal blend, that
is now you have
figured out, what
is a higher quality data source?
And what is a low
quality data source?
And you've created
a nice data mixture
using this information
about the quality
and information about how
many repeats you should see.
But you're not really showing
it in any particular order
to the model during
pre-training.
You're just showing
it in a random order.
And finally, our
two-phase approach
where you create
the optimal blend,
but you also make
sure that you show it
in a particular order,
where in phase 2,
you show more of the
high quality data source.
So you take care of quality
epochs and order in this.
And so this is the difference
between Pascal and Volta
that I was talking
about earlier, where
Pascal neither did he
estimate quality or epochs.
And he didn't follow any
particular order while learning.
Whereas Volta follows
a two-phase approach
and creates an optimal
data mixture from the data
that's available to her.
And if you do a
head-to-head comparison,
then Volta is on average
17% better compared
to Pascal and 3.4% better
compared to a random ordering.
But you have an
optimal data mixture.
So the next part of the talk
is front-loading reasoning.
And here we talk
about the synergy
between pre-training
and post-training data.
So the idea of
philosophy behind this
is that today's LLMs follow
this particular pipeline.
You have pre-training
where you try
to learn about world
knowledge and facts.
Supervised Fine
Tuning, SFT, where
you are learning to mimic
reasoning like answers or you're
basically learning
reasoning formatting.
And in RL finally, you
actually learn about reasoning.
And this in our
opinion where you're
doing only general knowledge
during pre-training
and in post-training is
where you add reasoning skill
as a post hoc thing.
That creates an unreasoning
foundation or a weak foundation.
So what we propose is
to front-load reasoning,
where in pre-training
you not only learn
about general knowledge, but you
also learn about reasoning skill
itself.
And then in post-training,
you can amplify and refine
this skill.
And this, we believe, would
lead to stronger foundation
for reasoning
models specifically.
So what is the study
that we have done
in front-loading reasoning?
We basically systematically
inject reasoning style data
at different phases of
the tree of the training,
like pre-training SFT and so on.
And we try to study, what is
the impact of adding reasoning
data at these different phases?
So this is the general
pipeline, that you have data,
pre-training SFT, and then RL.
And now you have access
to this reasoning data.
And we categorize
this reasoning data
along three axes, which
is diversity, quality,
and the quantity of
the reasoning data.
And, in this study,
what we do is
we try to understand the
diversity, quality, and quantity
of this reasoning
data to be added
in pre-training versus in SFT.
And what is the impact of it?
So in the next few slides, what
I'm going to be talking about
is that you have
this reasoning data.
And there are two conditions.
You either add it
in pre-training
or you don't add
it in pre-training.
If you don't add
it in pre-training,
then I'm going to call it
a no reason base, which
is that in your base model
when you're pre-training it,
you didn't see any
reasoning data.
And the second is
the reason base,
where in the
pre-training itself,
you've seen some amount of this
reasoning data, some quantity,
some quality, or some diversity
of this reasoning data
is added in pre-training.
And here I just wanted
to show this slide
on what evaluation
metrics we use
to evaluate pre-trained
models or post-trained models.
And the reason I'm
showing you this
is because there are
different benchmarks that
are used to evaluate base models
that is only pre-trained models.
And there are
different benchmarks
that are used to
evaluate models that have
undergone SFT, RL, and so on.
So when you see the numbers
in the next few slides,
they may be different for
pre-training and post-training.
So, what did we learn
from this study?
So first lesson is that
including reasoning data
in pre-training is beneficial.
So this is the comparison
between Volta and Ampere
right after you finish
your pre-training.
And so if you see, then
Ampere is doing 16%
on average better
compared to Volta.
That is the reasoning
base, that is
adding Ampere saw this reasoning
data during pre-training,
Volta did not.
And ampere got
16% gain right out
after the pre-training phase.
And that shows us that
adding this reasoning data
and pre-training
leads to improvement
in downstream accuracy.
But now it's not
enough that you just
see gains after pre-training.
What happens after SFT
and after post-training?
Do these gains just
get washed away
because you used reasoning
data and pre-training
and you also used reasoning
data in your SFT and so on?
So this is the comparison
for both of these cases.
No reason base and reason
base after doing SFT.
And after doing
SFT, as well Ampere
is still doing 9.3%
better compared to Volta.
And this tells us that the
advantage of adding reasoning
data to pre-training,
it doesn't get
washed away after you do
SFT, but it just grows.
The third lesson.
So for the third lesson,
I want you to again come
back to this axis
part that we had
three different axes for
categorizing reasoning data.
And based on this, we
have three datasets.
So one is SHQ, which is small
in quantity and diversity,
but it is high in quality.
The second is LDQ, which is
large in diversity and quantity
but low in quality.
And LMQ, which is a
concatenation of SHQ and LDQ.
You just combine them.
And so what we observe here
is that if you look at the bar
charts on the left side,
then the LMQ and LDQ,
they perform the
same on average.
That is adding this high quality
SHQ data to LDQ and forming LMQ,
it actually showed
as if there is
no benefit of adding this
high-quality data to LDQ right
after pre-training.
But if we post-train
the same models,
then we see that LMQ has a
4.25% boost compared to LDQ.
So what this tells us is
that high-quality data
in pre-training, it can
unlock these hidden gains
after doing SFT and you don't
necessarily lead to overfitting.
The fourth lesson is about
how early reasoning builds
a very strong foundation.
So now one can argue that hey,
you have this no reason base,
but what if you do
twice the amount of SFT?
Would that catch up?
Or what if you use
more data during SFT?
Would then you catch up?
And so on.
So there are these two cases
that we have discussed.
One where you use more
compute during SFT,
you use 2x amount number of
epochs in SFT for the no reason
base.
And for the reason base, you
just do one epoch of SFT data.
And you still see that you get
3% gains even after doing 2x
number of epochs
in the SFT phase.
So this is basically
using more compute in SFT.
And in the second case is where,
if your total data budget is
fixed, so you come and
say I have these fixed
number of documents.
And should I use all of them
in pre-training or should I
use all of them in SFT?
Or should I divide them?
So the graph on the right is
talking about this experiment
where it's data matched, that if
you keep all of your reasoning
data for SFT versus if
you split it and you use
some of it during
pre-training and some of it
during post-training, and you're
using the most highest quality
of data in the SFT phase here.
So even when you do
that, the reason base
basically performs
12% on average better
than the no reason base.
And what this tells us is that
this no reason pre-training
or basically pre-training
without using this reasoning
data, it cannot catch up by
getting more SFT compute.
And even when you have
fixed reasoning data budget,
it's better to always
use some amount
of that data in pre-training.
So the final lesson here is
that front-loading reasoning
creates a durable advantage.
And again, this
is the comparison
between final and
last comparison
between Ampere and Volta.
And this is after it has
gone through all the stages--
pre-training, SFT, and
RL, RLVR in this case.
So we see that after
doing all of these stages,
Ampere is still 19% on average
better compared to Volta.
And what, interestingly, we see
is that the gain has actually
ballooned for these very complex
math benchmarks like AIME, where
it's 39% better
compared to Volta.
So if we don't have any
questions on this part,
then I'll move to the last part
of the talk, which is RLP--
using reinforcement as a
pre-training objective.
Yeah.
So when we say small high
quality data [INAUDIBLE].
When we say small high
quality data and we say
medium high quality data, but
how to train this from a code
perspective when you
try to do pre-training,
how do you guys differentiate
between both of them?
How do we categorize
them into quality?
So we have used all
open-source datasets.
So there's OpenThoughts and
there is Nemotron SFT dataset
which is released.
So Nemotron SFT dataset has a
lot of data set mixed in it.
So it's diverse and it is
not very heavily filtered
like OpenThoughts.
So that's why it is lower
in quality in some sense.
And it has diversity
because it has many domains.
It's not just math and
not just code, and so on.
And yeah, it didn't go
through heavy filtering.
So it's lower in
quality compared
to at least OpenThoughts.
Yeah, it has far more
tokens than it's larger.
So that's how we categorized it.
But you can also
use we have also
done filtering in terms
of complexity, what
is more difficult
questions and so on based
on either the length, or if we
already have difficulty labels
and things like that.
So you can use these different
metrics to define quality.
Thank you.
Same question for classifying
data as reasoning data
is a methodology for deciding
that this kind of data,
because that might be
orthogonal to quality, or maybe
not completely orthogonal.
And then is the notion of
reasoning in the experiments
you've done domain independent?
You have legal
reasoning for the way
a lawyer reasons which
might be different from
how a mathematician or
how an empirical scientist
or an accountant or a
domain specific things.
Right.
So we have used like--
for reasoning data, we
use whatever definition
the community is using.
And as I said, we
have used datasets
that are already released in the
community as reasoning datasets.
But actually, from
my understanding,
typically, a lot of that data
looks like you have questions
and then you have
long reasoning traces
a final solution.
So like Math Olympiad
is a very good example.
A lot of that data looks
something like that.
And yeah, for domain
as well, yeah.
For the Nemotron SFT data, we
didn't do any domain filtering.
But I don't think we have
necessarily legal domain
and things like that.
A lot of it is STEM-focused--
math code, and other STEM areas
that are relevant to MMLU,
which is a benchmark,
and so on and so forth.
So yeah, that's the
composition of the data.
I'm wondering, do
you do automated data
mixtures/recipe optimization or
are these recipes handcrafted?
It's a mixture of both.
So all of the quality
estimation and Epoch
estimation that's automated.
And then we build a data
mixture based on those.
So that part is not completely
automated, I must say.
So by epoch
estimation, do you mean
how much of the total token
budget for each dataset?
Or do you mean--
How many repeats
of that data source
do you want to see before
you get diminishing returns.
So there are datasets where
if you see more than just two
repeats it, it will give
diminishing returns.
Whereas for some datasets,
you can do four repeats
or six repeats and so on.
Oh, that sounds amazing.
How do you estimate that?
So you can design an ablation
study where you have a base data
mixture, where you are just
using one repeat of that data,
and then you keep increasing
it like to two repeats, four
repeats, and so on.
And as you increase it, the wait
that, that data source gets,
that increases.
But then you have to take
away that much weight
from some other data source,
which is typically a low quality
crawl or something like that.
So you'll take
weight away from that
and give it to this
data source and try
to see if you do two repeats of
this, then what's the impact?
Four repeats of this,
then what's the impact?
And so on.
I see.
And you do this for each
domain in your corpus?
Yeah, we try to do it for
domain categories rather than
individual data sources.
Like so, for
example math, you'll
just do it for all of
math rather than there are
many data sources within math.
I see.
Thank you so much.
Out of curiosity, have you
tried the opposite approach
of quality first and
diversity afterwards
to see if-- because
you said first,
we go for Monte-Carlo
Markov chain.
You're doing exploration and
exploitation kind of thing.
And you got better
results by doing diversity
first and quality after?
Yeah.
So in the two-phase
approach, yeah, we first
want to do diversity
and then quality.
And then we did have an
ablation where we swapped that
and it didn't give
as good results.
Yeah.
So it's the opposite
of human beings, where
if you train a child
well, after that,
they can deal with rogue
behavior, whereas--
in that sense,
exploration first seems
to be doing the better job.
Yeah.
Awesome.
Then we can move
to the last part,
which is using reinforcement
as a pre-training objective.
So before I get started, I
just wanted to talk about,
what was the motivation for
this particular approach?
And I'd like to tell a story
of the tale of two learners.
One is Leo who learned
by doing things.
And second is Bolt who
learned by observing things.
Now one day there was a
task to build a bridge,
and you need to make
sure that this toy car is
able to pass across the bridge.
So Leo quickly grabs
a few stacks of blocks
and puts them
together and creates
this very simple bridge,
which is not at all fancy,
but it works because this
car is actually able to pass.
Bolt, on the other
hand, analyzes
every bridge that
has ever been made
and builds a
magnificent suspension
bridge, which is very fancy
design, flawless precision,
and so on.
But it was so tiny that the toy
car could not pass through it.
And so the lesson
here is about learning
by doing and not just watching.
And today's models, they learn
by watching text, that is just
predicting the next token.
Whereas the
motivation behind RLP
is to teach models to reason
through their own thoughts
and not just by observing text.
So the problem with the
standard pre-training.
So I've shown this
pipeline earlier
that you have pre-training where
you're gathering world knowledge
and you have SFT where you're
mimicking the reasoning format.
And you're essentially
doing imitation learning,
where if you predict
the next token, then
you get some kind of a reward.
Not RL reward, but yeah,
you get a yes or a no.
And you're doing this
pattern matching thing.
And only later during
the RLHF and RLVR phase,
that's when you're
actually doing reasoning
and you're giving the
ability to the model
to do any kind of exploration.
And that comes much later.
And so reasoning is
used as an afterthought
and added as a post hoc thing.
And the questions we
want to answer is that,
can reasoning be baked earlier
during pre-training itself?
And then of course, do these
gains actually last or are they
washed away after you
do the post-training?
This is also very important
because earlier, I
had shown this slide on
how the models today they
are consuming trillions
and trillions of tokens.
And so we have hit a wall
where we are using the most
number of tokens that we can.
And so now the question
is, how do you use them
effectively or efficiently?
And so RLP is one
of the solutions
for that as well where
maybe you need to learn to--
or develop data-efficient
algorithms.
And so what is the difference
between Vanilla pre-training
and RLP pre-training?
So you have this context
about photosynthesis
which is the process
plants, algae,
and some bacteria use to
make their own food using,
and what's the next token?
So in the standard
pre-training, you
would just predict the next
token given this context.
And you would say it's sunlight.
And that's just the
Vanilla pre-training way.
But in RLP, you give it
an opportunity to think,
an opportunity to explore.
And it thinks that,
you know what?
Photosynthesis actually
relies on solar energy.
And so the next token
must be sunlight.
So here you're basing
the probability
of the next token given
not only the context,
but the thought that was
generated by the model itself.
And this is
reasoning-driven prediction.
And this is RLP training.
So the key difference
is that RLP
produces an explicit reasoning
trace before predicting
the next token.
And this makes the why of it
very visible and trainable
and not just the final answer.
So this is a brief
overview of RLP.
And I'm going to go through each
of the components step-by-step.
But before that, I wanted to
show you the prompt that we
used to generate the thoughts.
So where we ask the model to
specifically focus on next steps
rather than jumping to this
final boxed answer and so on.
And we also ask the model not to
restate any question or metadata
commentary and so on.
So first is, what is
our thought policy?
What do I mean by that?
And so you have the prompt that
I showed on the previous slide.
You have the input,
which is the context.
And this goes into
the thought policy.
The thought policy
then does rollouts.
It gets the opportunity to
explore different thoughts
before it can predict
the next token.
So the thought policy does both.
It generates a thought and
then it generates a next token.
Now this same input
context without the prompt
is passed to the
no think baseline.
This is our standard next
token prediction model.
And given this input, it
calculates a probability
distribution on your
vocabulary and predicts
the next token sunlight.
So from the thought
policy, we get p theta,
which is probability of this
next token given the context, as
well as the reasoning trace
or the thought tokens that
were generated by the model.
And from the no
think baseline, we
get p phi which is the
probability of next token given
the context.
This is standard.
So based on these two--
p theta and p phi,
we calculate this information
gain-based reward.
So this is the information
gain-based reward
which is log of p theta
minus log of p phi.
And what's
interesting about this
is that if you
look at that term,
then it's positive only
when your thoughts actually
meaningfully
contribute to improving
the next token prediction.
So if the thought actually was
garbage or it didn't contribute,
then your reward can
be negative or even 0.
And as you can see, because
this is not your standard RLVR
kind of framing, where it's
not a 0 or one that you
get at the end, that
this reward is dense.
It can have any value.
And it can also be applied to
every position in the document
without needing any
external selection process.
So based on this
information gain,
you get rewards for each of your
rollouts, which I mentioned.
They are not binary,
they are dense.
And finally, the last
component of this pipeline
is exponential moving average.
So what is this
No-Think baseline?
This No-Think
baseline is basically
updated but with a delay.
It is the same as
thought policy,
but with a delay of
exponential moving average.
And the reason we choose this
is because we want the No-Think
baseline to be
current enough to be
able to provide
informative comparisons
during your training,
and it is also
intentionally lagged so that
we can mitigate reward hacking.
So that's the whole
pipeline of RLP.
And now to our experiments.
So the question is, can you
improve the reasoning ability
of a base model without
any task-specific tuning?
So over here we use the
Qwen 1.7B-Base model,
the final checkpoint.
And we do RLP training
for one billion tokens.
And we use general
pretraining corpora.
So now over here, we don't use
any reasoning-specific data
or anything.
You can use your web crawl.
You can use books,
papers, whatever you want.
And we show comparisons with
the baseline, of course.
We also show comparisons
after doing post-training
which is SFT and RLVR.
And we also show an
additional baseline,
which is that if you use 1
billion tokens to do RLP,
then what if you use the
same 1 billion tokens,
but do the next token
prediction loss?
That is, you just continue the
pre-training of the base model.
So we also show
comparisons with that.
And so here are the results.
RLP does show significant
improvement on the Qwen
31.7B-Base model.
And this is actually
the final comparison
between Ampere and Hopper.
And so when you do the base
model comparison, which
is the bar charts
on the left, RLP
does outperform the
base model by 19%.
And if you use those same tokens
to do next-token prediction,
then it still does better
than that by 17% on average.
And then when you do
identical post-training
which is SFT and RL, the
gains by RLP, the compound.
And Hopper does 8% better
relatively compared to Ampere.
So here the lesson
is that RLP is
able to establish robust
reasoning foundations
during pre-training
that are not washed away
by downstream alignment.
After doing SFT and RL,
they are not washed away.
So in the previous slide, I
showed token-matched comparison,
that if you do 1
billion tokens on RLP
LP versus 1 billion tokens on
next token prediction, then
you see improvements with RLP.
But the question is,
would these gains
sustain when you do compute
equivalent baselines?
What I mean by that is RL
typically takes more compute
compared to
next-token prediction
because you need to do
rollouts and you have
to do n number of rollouts.
You need to do completions to
generate this thought and so on.
So we calculate the
number of flops needed
using this equation here.
And now if I train RLP
with 170 million tokens,
then the flop-matched
equivalent tokens
there is 6 billion tokens.
That is I will use
6 billion tokens
to do next-token
prediction loss,
but I will use only 170
million tokens to do RLP.
So that's the comparison here.
So here are the results.
For TM is Token-Matched,
continuous pre-training
or next-token prediction
loss, basically.
And FM is Flop-Matched.
And so even for the
flop-matched case,
RLP outperforms next-token
prediction by 14% on average,
even though in this case,
next-token prediction loss is
exposed to 35x more data.
And so those were the results.
If you took the final
pre-trained checkpoint
and then did RLP.
Now the question is, what if you
take an intermediate checkpoint
of your pre-training run and
use limited data for RLP,
but compare it with the
final pre-trained checkpoint,
then would these gains sustain
and how would that work?
So we have intermediate
checkpoints for the Nemotron 12B
model v2, which is.
And so we take a
checkpoint that is trained
till 19.8 trillion tokens.
And we use RLP with
only 250 million tokens.
Again, we use general
pre-training corpora here.
And then we compare
it with the base model
that was trained till
20 trillion tokens.
So RLP in this case sees almost
$200 billion less tokens.
And then here are the results.
So RLP is scaling in
this case with LLM size
because this is much larger
compared to the Qwen results
that I showed earlier.
And also we have
scaled frameworks
because nano V2 is a hybrid
Mamba2-based model whereas Qwen
was a transformer model.
So again, here base has
seen 20 trillion tokens.
Base plus RLP has only
seen 19.8 trillion tokens
plus 250 million tokens.
So in this case, in
spite of being trained
on $200 billion
fewer tokens, Hopper
is still able to get a 35%
average gain over Ampere.
And as you can see,
you see largest
boost in domains like science.
And after doing
identical post training,
RLP still outperforms Base
by 3% absolute margin.
So the benefits of RLP
persist and maybe even
amplify when scaling to larger
models and across architectures.
So here is a little
bit of background
on the relevant
literature in this space.
The rise of early reasoning.
How early can we introduce
explicit reasoning the way
we have in RLP?
And so there are three
papers, at least at the time
our paper came out
in this space--
Quiet-STaR reinforcement
pre-training,
which is called RPT,
and reinforcement
learning on pre-training
data, which is called RLPT.
And then our method
is called RLP.
So here is a
qualitative comparison
between our technique,
RLP, and RPT and RLP.
So the source of reward.
So in next token prediction,
you have no reward.
Whereas in RPT and in RLPT,
you have an external verifier.
You will need different model
to calculate the rewards.
Whereas RLP is verifier-free
and it's intrinsic reward.
The granularity of
the reward, it's
sparse and binary
for RPT and RLPT
because they use
RLVR style rewards.
Whereas for RLP, as I
showed, it's a dense reward.
And finally, reasoning
emergence is explicit and weak
in case of RPT and RLPT,
but it's explicit and strong
for RLP.
And here is a
quantitative comparison
with the RPT technique.
So we have used a setting that
is similar to the RPT paper.
We use the Qwen31.7B-Base model
and we use the OmniMath dataset.
And we train using RPT
technique and RLP technique
on 170 million tokens.
And as you can see, RLP
is on average 4% better
compared to the RPT technique.
And the reason behind
this is that RPT actually
uses an external filter.
So it's using a
completely different model
to first go through
the pre-training data
and select the tokens on which
this RPT reward can be applied.
We do no such selection.
You can apply RLT reward on
any token in your document.
And RPT uses a
sparse binary reward.
It's just a yes or no, 0 or 1.
And reinforcing that
only select tokens
and it ignores the
reasoning steps itself.
Whereas in RLP, we apply
this dense per token reward
based on information
gain, as I showed earlier.
And that captures the
full reasoning signal
because we are taking the
reasoning trace into account
when we are
calculating the reward,
and that we believe
is the reason why
we get better results.
So the key ablations
and insights
that we discussed
for RLP is that first
is that we enable
thinking for itself,
exploring and thinking for
itself during pre-training
itself.
So you get an
incentive or a reward
for exploring and thinking.
So there's info gain reward
on intermediate thoughts.
And that outperforms simple
next-token prediction.
The reward in RLP is
dense and not sparse,
and it can be applied
at any position
or at all positions
in your document.
And there is token
efficiency because RLP
on 250 million tokens boosts
this Nemotron-12B by 35%,
whereas the comparison is with
20 trillion token baseline.
So the key takeaways
are that finally,
what is the comparison
between Pascal, Volta, ampere,
and Hopper?
So this is a very rough
percentage relative improvement
that you will see
between these four kids.
And as I said, they use
different learning strategies.
They have the same data, but
they use different strategies.
And so if you see
here, then for Hopper,
which she uses all
three strategies--
curriculum,
front-loading, reasoning,
and learning through
thinking, then you
can get as high as 60% relative
improvement over Pascal.
And finally, some
tangible takeaways here
are that your
two-phase approach is
very effective for
pre-training, where
phase 1 focuses on
diversity, phase 2
focuses on high quality data,
front-loading reasoning,
it does create durable
and compounding advantage.
And sometimes the gain
can be unlocked later
after the SFT phase.
RLP, on the other hand,
reframes RL for reasoning
as a pre-training objective.
And the goal there
was bridging this gap
between next-token
prediction and this emergence
of useful chain of
thought reasoning.
And it suggests that even
using unannotated text streams.
So in our paper, we
also show ablations
where, what happens if you
only use web crawl data?
What happens if you
use only academic data?
And so on.
And typically, we
do see a 7% to 9%
gain no matter what kind
of data you're using.
So even if you use unannotated
text streams like web crawl,
you can still teach
reasoning like behavior
while strengthening
the foundation.
And the post-training can
then build deeper expertise
or amplify that reasoning skill.
And finally, RLP brings
exploration and reasoning
incentives into pre-training,
allowing a model
to think through problems while
still building its knowledge
and understanding of the world.
So in pre-training,
you not only want
to do knowledge gathering and
understanding of the world,
but you also want the model to
explore and understand reasoning
during pre-training itself.
And this, we believe,
opens a new axis
for scaling in terms of
how models learn to reason.
And so finally, I
would like to leave you
with these four key components
of pre-training-- smart data,
smart architecture,
smart algorithms,
and smart collaborations.
And I'm happy to take
any more questions.
[APPLAUSE]
Do you have any questions?
Hi.
So I'm wondering about RLP.
So as you know, GRP
was a popular framework
for post-training.
So I'm wondering
if RLP, like when
you said it was generating
multiple different samples
and then you would calculate
an information gain,
which you could say analogously
is like the advantage in GRPO?
So I'm wondering if
there's any similarities
and what kind of contrast there
are to the post-training GRPO
technique with RPO?
Oh, yeah, we did use the GRPO
technique itself actually.
So in GRPO, you get a
reward, which is 0/1.
But now the way you're
calculating reward
is this information
gain-based reward.
And then the rest of the
advantage calculation
is very similar to how you
use GRPO in post-training,
where you are
calculating advantages
based on the probabilities
of the reasoning tokens
as well, and so on.
So all that remains the same.
The way you are
calculating reward
is the thing that has changed.
Just a quick question
is that, have you
tried doing RPL or any
of the other techniques,
like the first two
techniques you mentioned,
on vision language alignment?
No, not yet.
Yeah.
OK.
Sounds good.
Thank you.
Quick question on the RLHF.
Is RLHF still a preferred
way of using for LLMs
because with RLHF, there
is some kind of bias
of making humans feel better?
So is it still used for our
latest models in general?
So this is independent
of the RLP work.
From my understanding,
yes, a little bit
of the data and like RLHF
data is still used and mixed
into the RLVR and so on.
Different model families
use it in different ways.
But I would think
that it is still--
a part of it is still there
in the RL stage, basically.
So, is there a way we can
reduce this hallucination
of the bias from models
which are trained on RLHF
not to be too nice
with humans and more
be able to disclose the
information in a way
not to please the
humans or something?
The question is that, can we use
RLHF to reduce hallucinations?
Or t will RLHF increase
hallucinations?
Oh, I want to say in future,
when we have more models coming
up, how can we reduce this
bias which gets introduced
by RLHF into the models?
Is there a better
way to eliminate that
when interacting with users?
Instead of pleasing
the users, is
there a way we can have
better responses but still--
which helps the users instead
just making them feel better?
I see.
So in future, how do we
mitigate the hallucinations?
So I think that's an ongoing
work, from my understanding.
I don't work in that
space where people
are trying to build classifiers
of how helpful this thing is,
how also from the point of
view of safety and so on.
So yeah, I am not following
that work completely,
but my understanding is
you need to always keep
on updating those classifiers
because you can always
get adversarial data and so on.
And also like RLHF,
as I said, it's still
a part of the
post-training pipeline,
but it has become a
much smaller part.
Makes sense.
Thank you.
Yeah, I think that
has a lot to do
with alignment research,
which like folks at Anthropic
and so forth are focusing on.
Yeah, I think yeah,
RLHF is definitely
prone to things reward
hacking, but there's
a lot of ongoing work
on how to reduce that.
I can't think of
anything immediately
off the top of my head.
I there's things
like RLAIF, which
uses like AI instead
of humans, which
might be less subjective
and biased to some extent.
But yeah, I would check out some
of the work around alignment
and reducing reward hacking.
Hello.
Thank you for the talk.
Could you speak a
little more on how
you quantify quality of data
in say, mathematical context?
That's quite clear, but
you also spoke a lot
about using a web crawler
or other more general bodies
of data?
And how could you possibly
go quantifying quality
in that context?
Right.
So there are many
approaches here.
The most popular being fine
web EDU-based classification.
So Hugging Face released this
where they've built classifiers
to tell how educational is
this content, given a web crawl
document, it scores it
on a scale of 1 to 5.
So even at NVIDIA, we
have adapted that scaling.
So that's one way.
There's also essential
web that also did
more types of classifications
in terms of not just
educational quality or
educational score, but domains,
whether it belongs
to science or math.
And also even within
education, whether it's
like intermediate or high
college level education
and so on and so forth.
So it depends on yeah, what
do you want to extract?
And you can build a classifier--
LLM-based classification
on rubric for that.
And you can classify
your documents that way.
But fine web EDU is
the most popular one.
And that's at least basic one
that is needed in some sense.
Any more in-person questions?
When doing RLP, what do you
choose for your prefixes
to start with?
Do you do it by--
I'm assuming you do it on
the highest quality data,
but do you choose
specific tokens
or just uniformly
across that data set?
That's a good question.
So theoretically,
RLP can be applied
on any token in a document.
In practice, when we
run the experiments,
we take a document, we just
randomly choose a token.
We don't really select it
using some fancy techniques
based on entropy and so on.
So we randomly select a token,
we apply our RLP technique
on it.
We backprop the reward, and
then we throw away that document
and we just get a new document.
Yeah.
So that's how.
And also to correct
you, we are actually
not doing RLP on the
highest quality data,
as I've been saying it's been
done on the pre-training data
mixture.
So there is a lot
of web crawl in it,
and there's a lot of
other stuff in it.
It's not done only
on reasoning data.
We have an online
question that asks,
how far back can we likely go
in the RLP experiments and still
beat the CPT baseline, given
that the 19.8 trillion token
checkpoint is already over 1,000
times data to parameter ratio?
That's a great question.
So yeah, in the
paper, we present
results with the 19.8
trillion checkpoint.
But we did do experiments
on just 20% of pre-training.
So if 20 trillion is like
100% of pre-training,
then we do RLP on four
trillion token checkpoint?
And we still see gains
using RLP compared
to the baseline in some sense.
OK, great.
Any other questions?
So let's give another round
of applause to our speaker.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]